<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-28T00:22:29-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//</id><title type="html">Alisa in Tech</title><subtitle>I write about being in tech</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Explain Like I’m 5</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//eli5/2018/07/18/eli5-scd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explain Like I'm 5" /><published>2018-07-18T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-18T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//eli5/2018/07/18/eli5-scd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//eli5/2018/07/18/eli5-scd.html">&lt;p&gt;Explain like I’m 5 (ELI5) comes from the popular concept that if you really know something well, you can explain it simply, so a five year old can understand. I’ll try to do an ELI5 about Slowly Changing Dimension (SCD) to prove I know it well. Also, this post has the added benefit of preparing study material for five year olds who want to become data engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCD is a concept in data warehousing that aims to solve how to store information about a dimension as it changes over time. The rate of change is considered slow, although I don’t know if there’s a percise function for calculating its speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My nephew just turned five. He loves dinosaurs, so I’ll pretend I’m explaining SCDs to him. His name is Rhys In-tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Rhys, a dimension is just a fancy word for a person, place, or thing. It can be a thing that you can touch or a thing you can’t touch. You can touch your stuffed animals, they’re things, but a party is also a thing, but you can’t touch it. If you aren’t sure if something is a thing, try to put an “a” in front of it: a stuffed animal, a party, a car, a house. That’s a dimension!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a stuffed dinosaur is a dimension because it’s a thing. But we have lots of stuffed dinosaurs, so let’s say we wanted to list them. We may give them numbers (surrogate keys) like 0,1,2,3 and 4, but these don’t mean anything about the animal itself. It’s just so we can quickly identify them. Also, if we ever want to give the two dinosaurs the same name, their numbers would distinguish them&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we list our animals! We record their number and some stuff about them (attributes). Let’s record their name and their description&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bluey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Blue T-rex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pinky&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pink Triceratops&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes we may want to change our list. We may get new animals as presents! Or we may rename one. We would want our list to be up to date right? 
Adding a new animal is easy, we can just add it to the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachie&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachiosaurus&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy! But what if we want to rename one of our dinosaurs? That happens, doesn’t it? Well we have a few options of how to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Let’s call this way Type 1. In this way, we make a whole new list with the updated info. So if we want to rename Brachie to Bronchy, we would pull out a new piece of paper and write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bluey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Blue T-rex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pinky&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pink Triceratops&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bronchy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachiosaurus&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awesome! Only now if someone asked us about Brachie, we might not remember which one that used to be or when we changed his name. We don’t have any of his old data. If we lost a dinosaur and made a new list, we may forget that dinosaur ever existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we want to cross out the Brachie line lightly so we can still read his old name, and also write down the date that we crossed it out. That way, we can see his old name but we know it’s not real anymore.
Instead of crossing it out, let’s put an end date to show where we would have crossed it out, then we can add his new information under it (with a new fake number). Let’s also record when we got them as a start date! 
Like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Date we got it&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Date changed&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bluey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Blue T-rex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017-01-01&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pinky&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pink Triceratops&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017-01-01&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017-03-01&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachie&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachiosaurus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017-05-01&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018-07-18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broncy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachiosaurus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2018-07-19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it looks like you have 5 dinosaurs when you really don’t, but that’s okay. You just have to look at all the rows where there is no “date changed” date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have all the information we want recorded, but I guess it looks like you have five dinosaurs when you don’t, and if people think you have more than you really do, they might stop buying you gifts. I get that. 
What if we recorded both names? The old and the new? Like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Original Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;New Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bluey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Blue T-rex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pinky&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pink Triceratops&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velly&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachie&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brachiosaurus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Broncy&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have both names and we know we only have four stuffed animals! The only problem is– what if the description changes too? Do we have to make a new column for everything that changes? Also, what if we change the name again? Do we make another column or lose the first name?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally favor Type 2 best. Do you? I get that, but I really think your Auntie Katie will buy you stuffed animals no matter how many are on your list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; When I was younger, I had two similar stuffed dinosaurs that I named Cindy and Cindy because of my long held belief that twins were given the same name. My sisters said I even named my Barbies the same thing until they explained to me that twins, although they may look similar, are usually given their own names. Obviously the need for surrogate keys was present even in my childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of many sources potentially on the web for SCD: http://www.oracle.com/webfolder/technetwork/tutorials/obe/db/10g/r2/owb/owb10gr2_gs/owb/lesson3/slowlychangingdimensions.htm&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Explain like I’m 5 (ELI5) comes from the popular concept that if you really know something well, you can explain it simply, so a five year old can understand. I’ll try to do an ELI5 about Slowly Changing Dimension (SCD) to prove I know it well. Also, this post has the added benefit of preparing study material for five year olds who want to become data engineers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taylor Swift in Tech</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//taylor/2018/07/10/look.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taylor Swift in Tech" /><published>2018-07-10T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-10T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//taylor/2018/07/10/look</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//taylor/2018/07/10/look.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a silly post I wrote to make my friend James laugh. It is about relating a Taylor Swift song to duplicates in a database. You shouldn’t read too much into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you were to analyze it, and you shouldn’t, you may realize that Taylor Swift, the pop icon, is in sharp contrast with the engineering profession, which we usually associate with men. You may recognize that the song I chose, Look What You Made Me Do, is popularly considered to be written about Kanye West, who stole Swift’s microphone during her award acceptance speech. You may even overthink my choice of Taylor Swift as the artist, considering that she is a female in a male dominated industry whose accomplishments are constantly belittled by focusing on her romantic relationships and therefore her sexuality and femininity. But this tendency to disparage women, no matter how ubiquitous, is not relevant here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don’t like your little games&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Don’t like your tilted stage&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The role you made me play&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Of the fool&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;no, I don’t like you&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not like looking foolish, but duplicated data can be a silent killer. Most database systems stopped enforcing referential integrity constraints (primary keys and foreign keys), leaving us data engineers to our own devices. 
When we set up the data’s pipeline, we may QA it and declare its accuracy and perfection. But data can change in the source, and if we don’t notice, we may report metrics that make us look like a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don’t like your&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;perfect crime&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How you laugh when you lie  &lt;br /&gt;
You said the gun was mine  &lt;br /&gt;
Isn’t cool, no, I don’t like you (oh!)&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, duplicates are the perfect crime. If a field has a data type change, it is likely that the database will not insert the data and throw an error. If there’s a wrong number of fields, the insert statement will likely fail and throw an error. But the database doesn’t care what your data looks like as long as it fits the DDL, so duplicates can come right in. And thus, the perfect crime.
In most cases, the entire set isn’t duplicated because that may be too obvious. If a table doubles in size in a day, intuition alone can detect that error. Usually, a handful of records are duplicated because of a change that is limited to them, so the row counts and metrics can look reasonable, but reasonable is not accurate. So without an alert or a failure, and without an obvious change in the data, duplicated data gets away with its crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But I got smarter, I got harder in the nick of time&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Honey, I rose up from the dead, I do it all the time&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;I’ve got a list of names and yours is in red, underlined  &lt;br /&gt;
I check it once, then I check it twice, oh!&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you find a duplicate in a dataset and its cause, it’s time to get smarter. Every error that makes you look (or feel) like a fool should lead to action (and I don’t just mean deduplicating them). If the duplicates were caused by a change in the source data, find a way to automate checking the source database for changes. If it came from a change in the primary key, create an automated primary key checker.
So make a list of all the ways data has tricked you, and for every table, automate a test that ensures you’ll know immediately if they play the trick again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don’t like your kingdom keys &lt;br /&gt;
They once belonged to me  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You ask me for a place to sleep  &lt;br /&gt;
Locked me out and threw a feast (what!?)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to feel that we give data life only to have it sometimes turn on us; we give it a home, we clean it up, we aggregate it, and we even may put a pretty reporting tool on it.  So when data misleads us, we may be tempted to feel unappreciated. We may feel duped (ha), but we have to remember that part of giving data life is helping it grow up and mature, even through changes. So we may feel betrayed, we may feel like data begged us to be let in only to make us look foolish, but we should have done more for the data: giving it a place to sleep is not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The world moves on, another day, another drama, drama&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;But not for me, not for me, all I think about is karma  &lt;br /&gt;
And then the world moves on, but one thing’s for sure (sure)  &lt;br /&gt;
Maybe I got mine, but you’ll all get yours&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you fix the data by manually deduping it, you cannot just move on. The analysts will move on with their fixed data because they have reports to make, but you need to ensure it does not happen again– for this or any dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don’t trust nobody and nobody trusts me&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I’ll be the actress starring in your bad dreams  &lt;br /&gt;
I don’t trust nobody and nobody trusts me  &lt;br /&gt;
I’ll be the actress starring in your bad dreams&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is why you can’t just move on: the stakeholders trust you as the owner of the data. Mistakes happen, but a repeated violation of that trust can undermine how your organization interacts with the data. For every one wrong data set you provide, you have to provide a thousand perfectly correct ones just to maintain trust.
So automate your data quality checks. Know your data before and better than your analysts. Make sure people trust you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ooh, look what you made me do  &lt;br /&gt;
Look what you made me do  &lt;br /&gt;
Look what you just made me do&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Look what you just made me do&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, duplicated data makes us make a high quality, automated data quality checker that can anticipate any problem we have encountered before and that we can add new checks to. That is what duplicated data makes us do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a silly post I wrote to make my friend James laugh. It is about relating a Taylor Swift song to duplicates in a database. You shouldn’t read too much into it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Engineers and Analysts</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//engineering/2018/06/25/analysts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engineers and Analysts" /><published>2018-06-25T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-25T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//engineering/2018/06/25/analysts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//engineering/2018/06/25/analysts.html">&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on data engineers and their main stakeholders, whom I’m calling analysts. In some organizations, the main stakeholders may be data scientists or machine learning engineers, but the term analyst is not as bulky, so I’ll use that as a catch all. In addition, I’ll be using the term engineer to refer to data engineers, meaning any engineer who spends the bulk of his or her time focusing on data warehousing, ETL, or database management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should the relationship be between engineers and analysts? Good. That is the TL;DR. You are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay I’ll explain more what I mean. At the three companies at which I’ve been a data engineer and the one at which I’ve been a data analyst, I can say that the data structure tends to look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/funnel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;funnel&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: The approximate relationship between analysts and engineers. I made this myself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diagram shows there is no superior and inferior group; the relationship is not a hierarchy, it’s a machine with two parts. It’s a  machine that, when it works, allows two sets of people with related but distinguishable sets of skills to help a company optimize its data usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diagram shows one other thing: the two teams need to trust each other. Any two individuals working together have to know that, while one focuses on one’s part, the other part is covered well. Data engineers trust that analysts are giving them well written, top priority requests and querying the data to the best of their ability; analysts have to trust that data engineers are giving them good data. The more we trust, the less we look at what the other part is doing, and the more efficient we become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we do this build unity and trust? I am not suggesting you invite all the analysts to your monthly book club meeting; positive professional relationships can be cultivated more subtly than that. However, the book is Big Little Lies and the drink is Frose so, James, bring ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I have seen data engineers cultivate a good relationship with analysts: &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Make them your #1 stakeholder&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Help them with data QA&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Focus on your mutual goal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make them your #1 stakeholder&lt;/strong&gt;
I know, I know, we love all stakeholders equally. I really do believe all stakeholders bring something equal and individual to the company, but analysts are a special case. Referring back to the funnel, analysts can be seen as a combination of all other stakeholders; they funnel the top priorities from around the organization into requests. So prioritizing them is not special preference to one group, but rather special preference to already prioritized requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help them with data QA and maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;
You know what they say: fences make good neighbors, unless people start throwing bad data over them. 
We should help all groups with QA as is needed, but analysts are the only group that is not strictly one domain so they may need a little more help. Although we should always check that our data is reasonable and right against the source, when a marketing exec asks for marketing data, a reasonable assumption is that he or she knows it cold; our QA pales in comparison to their domain knowledge.
For general analyst groups though, they may not have the domain knowledge. They cover multiple subject areas and some are new to them. While an exec may have been working on a implementing a new project for months, the analysts might not hear about it until right before it goes live. So we should give them a little extra help with QA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on your mutual goal&lt;/strong&gt;
This should be obvious from the diagram: we are working on the same goal (I am so proud of that diagram; I’m going to ask my mum if she’ll hang it on the fridge). The KPIs need to be defined, the reports need to be made, and we have to do this together. So focus on that in every conversion, especially the hard ones. Invitations to help interview potential team members or invitations to meetings demonstrate an inclusiveness that won’t go unnoticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for how analysts can build a positive relationship with data engineers, virtually the same three tips apply with small tweaks:&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Be sure you’re representing data engineers fairly&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Help with data QA&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Focus on your mutual goal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only change is here is number 1: be sure you’re representing data engineers fairly. An analyst may talk to multiple departments and execs in one day, while I often have no meetings after stand up. This leaves bad analyst groups with a tempting choice: constantly blame back office for anything not on time or gone wrong. Data engineers are frequently not there to defend themselves, so they’re an easy target.
But I advise analysts not to give in to temptation; if you saw the funnel in half, nobody wins, especially not the company. Also, my mother said there’s no room on the fridge for the funnel because of my sister’s wedding stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post focuses on data engineers and their main stakeholders, whom I’m calling analysts. In some organizations, the main stakeholders may be data scientists or machine learning engineers, but the term analyst is not as bulky, so I’ll use that as a catch all. In addition, I’ll be using the term engineer to refer to data engineers, meaning any engineer who spends the bulk of his or her time focusing on data warehousing, ETL, or database management.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Swearing in Tech</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/22/swearing_in_tech.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Swearing in Tech" /><published>2018-04-22T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-22T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/22/swearing_in_tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/22/swearing_in_tech.html">&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we shouldn’t swear at work. If we lived in an ideal world though, I may not have a blog. And I do have a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, society has declared a subset of swears off limits. We have put substantial effort into eliminating words that offend minority groups, including people with disabilities. I remember seeing commercials, as a child, about ending the use of a certain word. I have long supported this trend, and I wonder, can we expand it to eliminating four-letter words that are offensive to women?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, they’re not all four letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some swears that derive their potency from their very femininity. Think about a swear word, specifically any of the many that pertain to or are about women. They may seem gender neutral; one may say they just mean “nasty” or “weak,” not anything specific to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do they mean these things? Why are they synonyms for nasty, weak, mean, immoral, gross, spineless, dirty? Because that’s how we view women’s characteristics. Women are either weak or pushy; lame or bossy; there is no in between. These words are offensive because women are offensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could argue that their origin is so far removed that, when using the word, one is not referring to the original, feminine meaning. Even if that were the case, I would still recommend not using them, and this is the main reason why and the reason for this post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one uses an offensive word that is based on female attributes, one may be talking to their genderless computer. But remember, the women in earshot may have heard that word in different context before; that word may have been used against them because of their femininity. It may have been used against them in situations in which they were intimidated or harassed for their femininity. So while one may not be using a word “like that,” the truth is, it is like that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ideally, we shouldn’t swear at work. If we lived in an ideal world though, I may not have a blog. And I do have a blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beer in Tech</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/09/beer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beer in Tech" /><published>2018-04-09T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-09T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/09/beer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/09/beer.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m wondering if beer in tech has reached its expiration date. Does beer expire? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I hate beer. It tastes like bitter wheat, it fills me up too quickly, and the fancy craft beer places always have lines. And I hate lines almost as much as I hate beer. But I think there are bigger issues here than my colleague’s taste in drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beer culture has somehow embedded itself into tech and startup culture. How often do the number of taps or the happy hours of a company appear on the “Join Us!” page of a tech company?  At $job-1, I received three bottle openers in my seven months there. The large, branded backpack they gave me at orientation had one, as though camping and drinking beer were my weekend hobbies; they gave me a branded keychain bottle opener; finally, at one point, they just gave me a branded bottle opener. The fact that beer related items were one of the ways they chose to brand themselves is telling of the relationship between tech and beer.&lt;br /&gt;
Branded items typically double as talent attraction tools in addition to traditional marketing tools. Listing happy hours is also a talent attraction tool. But who are these attracting? Are these tools sexist?&lt;br /&gt;
The obvious retort to “is beer sexist?” is simply “women like beer too!” Oh yes, some do. Some like beer a lot. Not every feminist is beer-hating like yours truly. There are beer-loving feminists, and they are great too. In fact, in college I had a beer-loving feminist as a roommate, and her rugby teammates who helped me move the keg out of the shower at 10 am were very nice. For follow up questions on why the keg was the in shower, please ask Lizzie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not the beer itself. It’s beer culture. If you do not believe me, Google “beer ads women.” Do it, I’ll wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, ask yourself:&lt;br /&gt;
Do the women in the images look like your wife, friends, mother? Do the men in the beer advertisements look like your husband, friends, father? Which gender is more realistically depicted? Do the advertisements seem to be appealing to women to drink beer, or are they appealing to men by using women as objects?&lt;br /&gt;
In researching this, I found a study (admittedly from 1994) titled ‘Women and “body-isms” in television beer commercials’ by Christine C. Iijima Hall and Matthew J. Crum. It found that beer commercials were more likely to show women’s bodies than men’s, even though men appeared more frequently than women. They were more likely to show men’s faces. Faces can display intelligence, while showing only body parts indicates a woman isn’t a full person, just a sum of parts available for men’s satisfaction.&lt;br /&gt;
Furthermore, for some reason, women appeared in bathing suits more often than men. As you know, bathing suits are in season for only a short amount of the year and certainly not professional attire. Why can’t women in beer commercials wear jeans? Why can’t they be…normal humans?&lt;br /&gt;
Hall and Crum broached the concern that these images could be dehumanizing and I agree. When women are treated as just decorative objects to support men’s hobbies (drinking and watching football), they lose their individuality. Women are not the hip-hop backup dancers of life, and any depiction of them as such should be immediately perceived for what it is: sexist garbage.&lt;br /&gt;
So beer advertisements are sexist garbage. But there is one step further we can take this. I’ll introduce the next topic with a story about my Alma Mater (Lizzie was there too).&lt;br /&gt;
At my school, as part of a larger effort to crack down on drinking, our college inexplicitly created a “Don’t be that girl” poster campaign. They put posters around the women’s dorms depicting drunk or hungover women being miserable, including of waking up in bed with a man with a face of regret. The posters were captioned: “You’re smart, Party smart.” The response from the female students must not have been passive and sweet; we received a campus-wide email defending the posters a few days after they appeared. By then, Lizzie had already stolen and hoarded any poster she found; I’m not sure they ever printed more. See below for a picture of me posing in front of some of our collection.&lt;br /&gt;
These posters had a thesis, and it was: you will be the victim of your own bad decisions if you drink too much. And women are told that in many ways, including victim-blaming for assault in high profile cases. It always come backs to how much the woman drank.&lt;br /&gt;
This is not to say that giving me a keychain brought up all these thoughts and made me mad. No, I kept that keychain because  it’s convenient. But this is women’s relationship with beer: being used as objects to sell it and then being told that, partaking in drinking it, opens up to guilt and shame.&lt;br /&gt;
So you see, from women’s perspective, beer time might not be the best perk, especially if it’s after work. Women are more likely to abstain from drinking altogether if they’re trying to conceive, pregnant, or breastfeeding. Since women still disproportionately handle child care and domestic duties, they may have to leave right when work ends. So by putting a magnifying glass on women’s relationship with beer, we can see that there are better ways to appeal to potential and actual female employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make happy hours take place before work ends as to not exclude those who have to rush home for family responsibilities (men too!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supply an equal amount of wine, beer, cider, and non-alcoholic drinks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refrain from having beer in the title; something like “social hour” is more generic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Displaying family-oriented benefits just as clearly and as often as beer-related websites, on your website and in interview conversations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/party_smart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;party-smart&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m wondering if beer in tech has reached its expiration date. Does beer expire? I don’t know.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Names in Tech</title><link href="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/05/name.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Names in Tech" /><published>2018-04-05T15:12:11-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-05T15:12:11-04:00</updated><id>https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/05/name</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alisa-in.tech//wit/2018/04/05/name.html">&lt;p&gt;Let me start by saying that I love my name. I love the way it sounds. I love being the only Alisa in any situation. I love that I wasn’t Alisa A. in elementary school. I would name my daughter Alisa, but, again, I love being the only one. But I considered changing my name on my resume and business cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading Breaking through Bias, a book about techniques for women at work. It cited the story of Kim O’Grady, who wrote “How I Discovered Gender Discrimination” about how adding Mr. to his resumes improved his job search. The book also cited studies that showed this phenomenon is not limited to Mr. Kim. And I believe the studies based on my experiences. So I thought- I should do this too. Anything to  put my best foot forward in this competitive tech industry, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is Kim is a unisex name. Alisa is not. Well, there may be deeper issues here, but I can’t tackle that right now. My name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alisa lends itself to very few nicknames, and those that apply are still strongly feminine. My family and friends usually call me Lisy. In the sing-song fashion of childhood games, my sisters would sometimes call me Lisy Lucy, which was later abbreviated to just Lucy. Occasionally my sister Christina will call me Lucifer, which I guess is technically masculine, but wouldn’t read well. I could shorten my name to just Al, but then people may wonder why my parents named me Al Aylward. It looks like a typo. The last realistic possibility is Lee, the middle syllable of my name. It doesn’t sound foreign to me and it goes with my last name. I can do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I realized I could go through with this, I began to feel a loss of identity. I could lie on my resume, the same way I could 
lie on my dating profile, but why would I debase myself by implying my true self isn’t my best self? Is it my best foot if it’s not
my foot? Are my cliches-turned-questions getting out of control? All things to consider in this experiment.
If I put Lee on my resume and a recruiter called me, would I always wonder if he or she would have called Alisa? Like lying on your dating profile, can you be sure that your first date would have come if he had known you own two cats and prefer staying in with them to going out drinking? That is a hypothetical question. Do I even want to work at a place that doesn’t want me? Or can we not fault people for subconscious biases that they don’t know they have, but instead work around them to get where we deserve to be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a woman is part of who I am, and it’s something of which I’m proud. I’m proud of my feminine traits, and I’m proud of being a woman in tech. 
I’m proud of the hurdles I’ve jumped over, and those that have tripped me. That’s what the Alisa on my resume means. (It also means my literal
name that matches my government issued ID). But I’m not proud of making 70 cents to the dollar. I’m not proud of my reaction to situations in which I perceived sexism. I’m not proud of my own self-deprecations, which maybe caused by my giving into how society sees me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no right answer here. It’s just another example of the moral issue of whether to bend to the majority’s subconscious biases in order to improve one’s perception within the group, or use one’s contradiction to their biases to educate them. And as long as there are biases, there will be moral ambiguity and no clear answers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Let me start by saying that I love my name. I love the way it sounds. I love being the only Alisa in any situation. I love that I wasn’t Alisa A. in elementary school. I would name my daughter Alisa, but, again, I love being the only one. But I considered changing my name on my resume and business cards.</summary></entry></feed>